STEFANIA VICTORIA COSTACHE

Contact: http://svcostac.github.io

Phone: +1 914 770 9589

Mail: stefania.costache@gmail.com

SUMMARY

I am a cloud technology freelancer with a research background in distributed systems and cloud resource management. I have experience with HPC, data analytics, cloud infrastructures and container cloud systems (Kubernetes, Mesos). I am interested in automatic, possibly data-driven, solutions to solve various issues from running heterogeneous workloads in the cloud: performance, cost effective resource management, resilience.

EDUCATION

PhD in Computer Science

2010 - 2013

University of Rennes 1, France

Funded by EDF (French Electricity Company)

Advisors: Christine Morin, Nikos Parlavantzas and Samuel Kortas

PhD Thesis title: "Market-based autonomous resource and application management in the cloud"

Master of Computer Science

2008 - 2010

Automatic Control and Computers Faculty University "Politehnica" of Bucharest, Romania

Specialization: System Software and Advanced System Applications

Bachelor of Engineering

2003 -2008

Automatic Control and Computers Faculty University "Politehnica" of Bucharest, Romania

Specialization: Computers

SKILLS

Programming Languages/Technologies: C, C++, Java, Golang, Python, Scala.

• Familiar with Ansible, MySQL, shell, Jupyter Notebook

Cloud Platform: Kubernetes, Mesos, Docker, Spark

• Familiar with IBM Cloud, Google Cloud, AWS, Microsoft Azure, OpenStack, Hadoop, NoSQL datastores, Flink, Pytorch, AutoML technologies

EXPERIENCE

Freelancer, Sweden

January 2019 - present

Projects related to cloud and machine learning technologies

IBM T.J.Watson Research Center, New York, US

January 2016 - November 2018

Research Staff

- I lead the architecture design and implementation of solutions to use spot market concepts in resource management to maximize the efficiency of the cloud infrastructure for serverless data analytics and deep learning workloads.
- I experimented with container orchestration frameworks (Mesos, Kubernetes), prototyped custom controllers and schedulers, designed scalability experiments and investigated using machine learning for workload performance estimations and scheduling.

Chalmers University of Technology, Sweden

September 2015 - December 2015

Postdoctoral Researcher

• I lead an investigation on the performance of stream processing frameworks (Spark and Flink) in the IoT context using intelligent vehicular systems as experimental case study and outlining the advantages and limitations of the different technology stacks.

Vrije University Amsterdam, The Netherlands

Postdoctoral Researcher

- I developed an online scheduler for scientific data-intensive workflows, integrated with an elastic in-memory data storage, a solution that leads to increased scheduling performance and minimized resource waste of the workflow.
- I implemented a simulator for multi-cloud provisioning policies for heterogeneous workloads, showing that sharing larger virtual machines of different types across applications leads to hosting cost reductions.
- Several other projects I was involved in: analysis of scalability of cloud stacks, algorithms for profiling the energy consumption and performance of many tasks computing applications, elastic in-memory data storage.

INRIA Rennes-Bretagne Atlantique, France

September 2013 - January 2014

Research Engineer

 I designed and ran scalability experiments of a cloud middleware software that interfaces multiple infrastructure clouds (European funded project), showing that the middleware brings low performance overheads for a typical application deployment while decreasing configuration overheads for users.

EDF R&D/INRIA Rennes-Bretagne Atlantique, France

May 2010 - July 2013

Research Engineer

- I designed a resource management framework for running HPC applications (batch MPI and task farming) on a private cloud using spot market and virtual economy concepts for prioritizing and scaling application resources.
- I proposed SLO-driven scaling policies for vertical (in terms of CPU and memory per virtual machine) and horizontal (in terms of number of virtual machines) resource allocation, allowing more users to run applications at the same time and leading to maximized utilization of the infrastructure.
- I developed a incremental placement algorithm for virtual machines that reduced the number of virtual machine migrations below a threshold, thus decreasing resource management performance overheads noticed by applications.
- Results were published in several top-tier conferences and journals.
- Awarded as the Best paper on Cloud Computing from the french academic community, at the annual meeting ComPAS 2014.

INRIA Rennes-Bretagne Atlantique, France

May 2009 - October 2009

Intern in the Myriads Group

- I designed a high availability framework for stateful geo-distributed services in large scale distributed systems.
- Large scale tests of the framework on geographically distributed resources showed that services
 experienced low latency overheads and an improvement in the number of reconfiguration decisions
 due to nodes leaving or failing.
- Results were published at a top-tier domain specific conference.

University of Groningen, The Netherlands

Intern in the Molecular Dynamics Group

February 2009- March 2009 March 2008 - July 2008

- I designed a parallel implementation of multiscale algorithms for molecular dynamics simulations used for scientific research.
- Large scale runs showed significant reduction in simulation time.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Vrije University Amsterdam, The Netherlands

- Lecturer for the Advanced Topics in Distributed Systems course, (2nd year master), Fall 2014
- Teaching Assistant for the Performance of Networked Systems course, (1st year master), Spring 2014, 2015

"Politehnica" University of Bucharest, Romania

- Computer Graphics (3rd year course), Fall 2008
- Graphic Processing Systems (4th year course), Fall 2008
- Operating Systems (3rd year course), Fall 2007

PUBLICATIONS

- Resource Management in Cloud Platform as a Service Systems: Analysis and Opportunities. <u>Stefania Costache</u>, Djawida Dib, Nikos Parlavantzas, Christine Morin. *Journal of Systems and Software*, Elsevier, 2017.
- MemEFS: A network-aware elastic in-memory runtime distributed file system. Alexandru Uta, Ove Danner, Cas van der Weegen, Ana-Maria Oprescu, Andreea Sandu, <u>Stefania Costache</u>, Thilo Kielmann. Future Generation Computer Systems, Elsevier, 2017
- Market-based autonomous resource and application management in private clouds. <u>Stefania Costache</u>, Samuel Kortas, Christine Morin, Nikos Parlavantzas. *Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing*, 2016
- Understanding the data-processing challenges in Intelligent Vehicular Systems. Stefania Costache,
 Vincenzo Gulisano, Marina Papatriantafilou. Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IV), 2016 IEEE, pp. 611--618
- E-BaTS: Energy-Aware Scheduling for Bag-of-Task Applications in HPC Clusters. Alexandra Vintila-Filip, Ana-Maria Oprescu, <u>Stefania Costache</u>, Thilo Kielmann. Parallel Processing Letters 25(03), 1541005, World Scientific, 2015
- MemEFS: an elastic in-memory runtime file system for escience applications. Alexandru Uta, Andreea Sandu, <u>Stefania Costache</u>, Thilo Kielmann . e-Science 2015, pp. 465--474
- Scaling vm deployment in an open source cloud stack. Kaveh Razavi, <u>Stefania Costache</u>, Andrea Gardiman, Kees Verstoep, Thilo Kielmann. Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Scientific Cloud Computing, pp. 3--10, 2015.
- Merkat: A Market-based SLO-driven Cloud Platform. Stefania Victoria Costache; Nikos Parlavantzas;
 Christine Morin; Samuel Kortas. CloudCom 2013, Bristol, United Kingdom
- On the Use of a Proportional-Share Market for Application SLO Support in Clouds. Stefania Victoria Costache; Nikos Parlavantzas; Christine Morin; Samuel Kortas. EuroPar2013, Aachen, Germany (acceptance rate 26.8%)
- Themis: Economy-Based Automatic Resource Scaling for Cloud Systems. Stefania Victoria Costache;
 Nikos Parlavantzas; Christine Morin; Samuel Kortas. HPCC 2012, Liverpool, United Kingdom (acceptance rate 26.2%)
- An Economic Approach for Application QoS Management in Clouds. Stefania Victoria Costache; Nikos Parlavantzas; Christine Morin; Samuel Kortas, VHPC 2011, Bordeaux, France.
- Semias: Self-Healing Active Replication on Top of a Structured Peer-to-Peer Overlay. Stefania Costache, Thomas Ropars, Christine Morin, SRDS 2010, New Delhi, India (acceptance rate 21%)
- Multiscaling Algorithms for Molecular Dynamics Simulations with GROMACS. Nicolae Goga, Siewert Marrink, Stefania Victoria Costache, Florica Moldoveanu, IEEE International Systems Conference, 2009, Vancouver, Canada

ADDITIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Reviewer for International Journal of Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems since 2016
- External reviewer for the following conferences: IPDPS (2011, 2012), ISPDC (2011), Cluster (2011), CCGrid (2012, 2013) and the VTDC workshop (2012).

LANGUAGES

- English (fluent)
- French (intermediate)
- Romanian (native)